<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
     draft-rfcxml-general-template-annotated-00

     This template includes examples of most of the features of RFCXML with comments explaining
     how to customise them, and examples of how to achieve specific formatting.

     Documentation is at https://authors.ietf.org/en/templates-and-schemas
-->
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>  <!-- Required for schema validation and schema-aware editing -->
<!-- <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?> -->
<!-- This third-party XSLT can be enabled for direct transformations in XML processors, including most browsers -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- If further character entities are required then they should be added to the DOCTYPE above.
     Use of an external entity file is not recommended. -->

<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  docName="draft-augustyn-intarea-ipref-02"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates=""
  submissionType="IETF"
  category="std"
  consensus="true"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">
<!--
    * docName should be the name of your draft
    * category should be one of std, bcp, info, exp, historic
    * ipr should be one of trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902, pre5378Trust200902
    * updates can be an RFC number as NNNN
    * obsoletes can be an RFC number as NNNN
-->

  <front>
    <title>IP Addressing with References (IPREF)</title> <!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#title-4 -->
    <!--  The abbreviated title is required if the full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-augustyn-intarea-ipref-02"/> <!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#seriesinfo -->
    <!-- Set value to the name of the draft  -->

    <author fullname="Waldemar Augustyn" initials="W" role="editor" surname="Augustyn"> <!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#author -->
    <!-- initials should not include an initial for the surname -->
    <!-- role="editor" is optional -->
    <!-- Can have more than one author -->

    <!-- all of the following elements are optional -->
      <address> <!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#address -->
        <email>waldemar@wdmsys.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2023"/> <!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#date -->
    <!--<date year="2023" month="2" day="5"/>--> <!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#date -->
    <!-- On draft submission:
         * If only the current year is specified, the current day and month will be used.
         * If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, the current day will
           be used
         * If the year is not the current one, it is necessary to specify at least a month and day="1" will be used.
    -->

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <!-- "Internet Engineering Task Force" is fine for individual submissions.  If this element is
          not present, the default is "Network Working Group", which is used by the RFC Editor as
          a nod to the history of the RFC Series. -->

    <keyword>IPREF</keyword>
    <!-- Multiple keywords are allowed.  Keywords are incorporated into HTML output files for
         use by search engines. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes IP addressing with references (referred to as IPREF) and how it
        can be used with IPv4 and IPv6. It uses special addresses called IPREF addresses which
        use references to IP addresses instead of actual addresses. IPREF provides highly scalable
        means of traversing private address spaces end-to-end. It can traverse private address
        spaces both within the same protocol domain and across protocol domains. For example, it
        allows NAT traversal for IPv4, or for IPv6 with NAT6 or filters. It also allows direct
        communication between IPv4 and IPv6 networks, including over NAT, NAT6, or filters.
      </t>
      <t>IPREF addresses are publishable via Domain Name System (DNS). Any host on any private
        network may publish its services via DNS. These services are reachable from any network,
        whether IPv4 or IPv6, provided IPREF is supported on both ends.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section>
    <!-- The default attributes for <section> are numbered="true" and toc="default" -->
      <name>Introduction</name>

      <t>Most hosts on the Internet are actually not directly attached to the Internet. Instead
        they reside on local networks that are attached to the Internet through some sort of
        a firewall that limits external access to them. In the IPv4 case, the firewall commonly
        runs Network Address Translation (NAT). In the case of IPv6, it may be filters but it
        also may be NAT6 behaving similarly to NAT. Whichever the case, peer-to-peer connectivity
        is greatly limited. This creates a problem commonly referred to as NAT traversal.
      </t>
      <t>For common services, especially those advertised through Domain Name System (DNS), the
        problem is solved by exposing local servers to the Internet as if they were residing
        directly on the Internet. The solution works because it relies on the client server
        nature of these services. In this model, the servers wait until some host initiates
        a connection. Firewalls and NAT make sure the return path for the packets is open. The
        servers don't initiate connection on their own (unless to other servers that are
        already exposed to the Internet).
      </t>
      <t>For peer-to-peer applications, there is no general solution. Instead, there is a hodgepodge
        of half solutions suitable for selected cases, none of them scalable. They mostly attempt
        to temporarily expose internal hosts at the edge router's address and some specific port,
        or deduce if such an exposure exists which then may be passed to applications that can
        make use of such information.
      </t>
      <t>There is a similar problem when attempting to traverse different protocol domains, such
        as IPv4/IPv6. It is a somewhat harder problem to solve given different protocols in play.
        One attempt to do that, known as NAT64/SIIT, illustrates the difficulties. The result
        cannot be even called a solution as it is severely constrained. It is more of a study. It
        requires external translation devices through which all traffic must go, and which
        require configuration that needs to be externally maintained. It does not scale beyond
        very small setups. It also requires allocating global IPv4 addresses for IPv6 peers.
      </t>
      <t>All of these attempted solutions suffer great difficulties because they try to render
        necessary address transformations too early. IPREF takes a different approach. It is
        based on the observation that the originating hosts actually do not have to know what the
        destination addresses are, or what protocol they belong to, so long as they can be referred
        to in a manner understood by both ends. Thus, IPREF uses references to addresses rather
        than real addresses. This allows to delay the rendering of necessary transformations until
        a proper context is available. This approach works not only for NAT traversal but also for
        protocol traversal since both problems are actually about the same problem: traversing
        different address spaces potentially in different protocol domains. The protocol domain
        matters only to the extent that a sufficient compatibility exists between the protocols
        that packet payloads may be repackaged from one to the other while keeping functionality
        of higher level protocols, such as TCP/UDP, intact. Such a compatibility exists between
        IPv4 and IPv6.
      </t>
      <t>With this approach, IPREF does not need to negotiate anything. It does not need any
        external devices, any external configurations. It does not require allocating any
        global IP addresses from involved protocols. The result is a highly scalable solution
        that works over NAT, NAT6, filters, and across IPv4/IPv6.
      </t>
      <t>In practical implementations, all IPREF processing is vested with gateways designated for
        the purpose. The gateways may be the same as network edge routers but they may also reside
        inside the networks, behind the edge routers and firewalls ("behind NAT"). The gateways
        deal with processing of references and with any address mapping. If protocol conversion is
        necessary, they run dual stacks and perform payload repackaging between the protocols. The
        references, along with context addresses passed with them, are called 'IPREF addresses' to
        distinguish them from native addresses. The gateways translate both source and destination
        IPREF addresses to native addresses of the local network protocol before injecting packets
        to local networks.
      </t>
      <t>The rest of the hosts on the network are standard hosts running whichever local network
        protocol is employed, IPv4 or IPv6. They never see IPREF addresses or references. They
        are completely oblivious to any IPREF processing taking place at the gateways. They do not
        need to run dual stacks, nor is there any advantage doing so. They may run just a single
        stack which could lead to lowering the cost of building and maintaining networks.
      </t>
      <t>IPREF addresses are publishable via DNS. Such publishing does not consume any global
        addresses of any network protocols. Any host on a private network may publish services
        at any port they wish. For example there maybe five different hosts publishing web
        services at port 443 and all five will be reachable at that port and all five may
        advertise their services via DNS.
      </t>
      <t>Publishing without consuming global IP addresses is very attractive for IPv4 but there
        are more reasons to publish as IPREF which apply equally to IPv4 and IPv6. Chiefly among
        them is cross protocol reach. Such services may be accessed from IPv4 and IPv6 clients
        which is very useful in any transition strategy. Further, IPREF references are very light.
        They may be allocated and discarded easily, at will, or at time intervals. They may expire,
        may be shadowed by different references pointing to the same services. They may be
        preferable over exposing internal IP addresses for security reasons. They could be used
        to help fighting Denial of Service (DoS) attacks. They could be used for A/B marketing
        testing, or they could be used with authenticated DNS servers to identify different classes
        of users for marketing purpose, forensic purpose, or service level purpose, etc.
      </t>
      <t>IPREF allows development of new, specialized protocols by providing interoperation with
        existing IP networks. Because IPREF does not require negotiations of any sort and it does
        not depend on any time domain, it is suitable for developing a range of specialized
        network protocols for special requirements networks such as space networks, IoT networks,
        high security financial or military networks, etc.
      </t>

      <section anchor="requirements">
      <!-- anchor is an optional attribute -->
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
          RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
          interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
          all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
      <!-- The 'Requirements Language' section is optional -->

      <section anchor="terminology"><name>IPREF Terminology</name>
        <t>IPREF - short name referring to the technology described in this document, pronounced I-P-REF</t>
        <t><em>encoding</em> network - network representing hosts on peer private networks</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section><name>IPREF Overview</name>

      <t>IPREF is a method for communication across different address spaces, i.e.: address
        spaces that are not reachable by native network protocols. Examples are private networks
        behind NAT, NAT6, or filters, as well as networks employing different network protocols
        IPv4/IPv6.
      </t>
      <t>Key characteristics of IPREF:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>massively scalable</li>
        <li>cross protocol, cross address space (such as NAT/NAT6)</li>
        <li>strictly layer 3 (no port manipulation, all ports available)</li>
        <li>addresses publishable in DNS</li>
        <li>no need for external translators or shared configurations</li>
        <li>no need for any global addresses IPv4 or IPv6</li>
      </ul>

      <section><name>References</name>

        <t>A common problem with cross address space communication is to decide how to deal with
          addressing. Communicating peers cannot interpret each other's addresses therefore some
          other method of directing packets to proper destinations must be devised.
        </t>
        <t>IPREF solves this problem by using references to addresses rather than actual
          addresses. The references are then evaluated by each address space to render proper
          native addresses suitable for forwarding. Each address space performs the evaluation
          independently. As a result the same references render different addresses at different
          address spaces.
        </t>
        <t>References are unsigned integers meaningful only in the context of the address space
          where they were defined. Local administrators may divide their values into fields for
          any purpose believed useful. For example, the fields may reflect different sources of
          allocations, or provide extra security bits, or provide load balancing options, or
          provide A/B address ranges etc. Peers are unaware of these fields and treat the
          references as opaque values.
        </t>

      </section>  <!-- ^^ References ^^ -->

      <section><name>IPREF Addresses</name>

        <figure anchor="ipref-address"><name>IPREF address</name>
          <artwork type="ascii-art"> <![CDATA[
         â”Œâ”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”¬â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”
         â”‚  context address  â”‚     reference     â”‚
         â””â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”´â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”˜
            198.51.100.11 + 700
            2001:db8::abc:11 + 700
          ]]> </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>IPREF uses references to addresses in lieu of actual addresses. Such references need
          context to be meaningful, therefore IPREF uses addressing units that combine a context
          address, which MUST be a native address, and a reference. These addressing units are
          called IPREF addresses.
        </t>
        <t>The context address portion of an IPREF address is an address within adjacent address
          space. Typically, this is the Internet, so this is usually an Internet address of an
          edge router of the source or destination network. This is a convenience, not a
          requirement, other addresses known to the network may also be used.
        </t>
        <t>References are allocated by administrators of respective address spaces. The references
          may only refer to hosts from those address space. Thus, the destination references are
          allocated by the administrators of the destination networks while the source references
          are allocated by the administrators of the source networks. There are no conflicts and
          there is no need for negotiations. Each peer defines their own references and accepts
          peer references as opaque values.
        </t>
        <t><xref target="ipref-address"/> shows two examples of IPREF addresses. In the notation,
          a plus sign '+' separates context address from the reference. A packet carries two
          addresses: source IPREF address and a destination IPREF address.
        </t>
        <t>IPREF addresses are publishable in DNS.
        </t>

      </section>  <!-- ^^ IPREF Addresses ^^ -->

      <section><name>Gateways and Encoding Networks</name>

        <t>IPREF addresses are placed in packets by gateways. The gateways must be installed at
          each address space participating in IPREF communication. Intermediate address spaces,
          such as the Internet, don't need gateways.
        </t>
        <5>The gateways inject and remove IPREF addresses as packets leave and enter local
          networks. They also encode IPREF addresses for internal use as local network protocols
          only understand native addresses. The encoding networks are local private networks to
          which the gateways map IPREF addresses. For example, IPv4 networks could use a 10/8
          network while IPv6 networks could use an fd::/64 network. For local hosts, these
          encoded addresses represent peers they communicate with. The peers appear as if on
          the local network. This is a common consequence of cross protocol communication. The
          gateways replace these encoded addresses with IPREF addresses when sending packets
          outside local networks.
        </t>

      </section>  <!-- ^^ Gateways and Encoding Networks ^^ -->

      <section><name>Traversing Address Spaces</name>

        <t>Conceptually, packets travel through address spaces based on source and destination
          IPREF addresses. This is analogous to IP protocols. The IPREF addresses are interpreted
          at each address space to render native addresses suitable for forwarding.
        </t>

        <figure anchor="traversing-address-spaces"><name>traversing address spaces</name>
          <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
             Network A    â”‚    Internet    â”‚    Network B

src:  2001:db8::9 + 1579   2001:db8::9 + 1579   2001:db8::9 + 1579
dst:  2001:db8::8 + 2466   2001:db8::8 + 2466   2001:db8::8 + 2466

           ðŸ¡³                    ðŸ¡³                    ðŸ¡³

src:  172.17.1.75          2001:db8::9          fdee:eeee::5951
dst:  10.128.48.62         2001:db8::8          2001:db8:b::28


 â”Œâ”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”        IPv4     â”‚      IPv6      â”‚     IPv6        â”Œâ”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”
 â”‚ host â”‚.75â”ƒ                                            â”ƒ   â”‚ host â”‚
 â”‚  A1  â”œâ”€â”€â”€â”¨  â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“  â”‚                â”‚  â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“  â” â”€â”€â”€â”¤  B4  â”‚
 â””â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”˜   â”ƒ  â”ƒ IPREF â”ƒ:9                  :8â”ƒ IPREF â”ƒ  â”ƒ   â””â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”˜
            â” â”€â”€â”¨ g-way â” â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€  Internet  â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”¨ g-way â” â”€â”€â”¨
 â”Œâ”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”   â”ƒ  â”ƒ  GWA  â”ƒ                      â”ƒ  GWB  â”ƒ  â”ƒ:28â”Œâ”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”
 â”‚ host â”œâ”€â”€â”€â”¨  â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›  â”‚                â”‚  â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›  â” â”€â”€â”€â”¤ host â”‚
 â”‚  A3  â”‚   â”ƒ                                            â”ƒ   â”‚  B6  â”‚
 â””â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”˜                 â”‚                â”‚                 â””â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”˜

          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>For example, in <xref target="traversing-address-spaces"/>, if host A1 wanted to
          send a packet outside of its own address space to host B6, it would need a source
          IPREF address for itself and a destination IPREF address for B6.
        </t>
        <t>The destination IPREF address of host B6, presumably a server, would be allocated
          by the admin of network B where B6 resides. It would normally be advertised in DNS.
          The source IPREF address of A1, presumably a client, would normally be allocated
          dynamically by the local IPREF gateway.
        </t>
        <t>As packets travel from source to destination, the following takes place:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>At network A, the IPREF source address is interpreted as a native address of host
            A1. The destination IPREF address is interpreted as some local private address on
            the encoding network. This allows host A1 to place native addresses in the packet.
            The IPREF gateway will replace both source and destination addresses with their
            IPREF equivalents. It will also repackage IPv4 packets into IPv6 since the next
            address space is IPv6.
          </li>
          <li>In the transient address space, the Internet, IPREF addresses are interpreted
            as well even though the network is unaware of that. In the transient networks
            only context addresses are used while the references are ignored. This is
            accomplished by placing context addresses (which must be native) in the respective
            source and destination fields of the native network protocol. In this way, transient
            networks, such as the Internet, don't need to know anything about IPREF.
          </li>
          <li>At network B, the IPREF source address is interpreted as some local private address
            on the encoding network. The IPREF destination address is interpreted as the native
            address of host B6. In this way, a packet originating at an IPv4 host A1 reaches an
            IPv6 host B6.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>On the way back, source and destination addresses are reversed and their interpretation
          follows the same pattern, thus a reply packet originating at an IPv6 host B6 reaches an
          IPv4 host A1.
        </t>
        <t>In the example, network A may be IPv4 or IPv6, the Internet may be IPv4 or IPv6, and
          network B may be IPv4 or IPv6. In any combination, a packet traveling through these
          address spaces would be processed in the same manner and it would reach its destination
          in the same way.
        </t>

      </section>  <!-- ^^Traversing Address Spaces^^ -->

      <section><name>Traversing Address Spaces in Detail</name>

        <figure anchor="traversing-address-spaces-in-detail"><name>traversing address spaces in detail</name>
          <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
             Network A    â”‚    Internet    â”‚    Network B

 â”Œâ”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”        IPv4     â”‚      IPv6      â”‚     IPv6        â”Œâ”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”
 â”‚ host â”‚.75â”ƒ                                            â”ƒ   â”‚ host â”‚
 â”‚  A1  â”œâ”€â”€â”€â”¨  â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“  â”‚                â”‚  â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“  â” â”€â”€â”€â”¤  B4  â”‚
 â””â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”˜   â”ƒ  â”ƒ IPREF â”ƒ:9                  :8â”ƒ IPREF â”ƒ  â”ƒ   â””â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”˜
            â” â”€â”€â”¨ g-way â” â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€  Internet  â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”¨ g-way â” â”€â”€â”¨
 â”Œâ”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”   â”ƒ  â”ƒ  GWA  â”ƒ                      â”ƒ  GWB  â”ƒ  â”ƒ:28â”Œâ”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”
 â”‚ host â”œâ”€â”€â”€â”¨  â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›  â”‚                â”‚  â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›  â” â”€â”€â”€â”¤ host â”‚
 â”‚  A3  â”‚   â”ƒ                                            â”ƒ   â”‚  B6  â”‚
 â””â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”˜                 â”‚                â”‚                 â””â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”˜


Internet ifc: 2001:db8::9                 Internet ifc: 2001:db8::8
Local net A:  172.17.1.0/24               Local net B:  2001:db8:b::/64
Encoding net: 10.128.0.0/10               Encoding net: fdee:eeee::/64
Host A1:  172.17.1.75                     Host B6:  2001:db8:b:28
DNS A1:   (none)                          DNS B6:   2001:db8::8 + 2466
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Let's say an IPv4 host A1 wants to send a packet to an IPv6 host B6:</t>
        <ol>
          <li><t>Host A1 finds out the address of host B6</t>
            <t>Host A1 issues a DNS query for host B6. The query goes through the local resolver.
              Local resolver receives a response:
            </t>
            <sourcecode>B6 has address: 2001:db8::8 + 2466</sourcecode>
            <t>Since local hosts don't understand IPREF addresses, the resolver asks gateway GWA to
              allocate an encoded address for it. The gateway responds:
            </t>
            <sourcecode>map: 2001:db8::8 + 2466  =  10.128.48.62</sourcecode>
            <t>The resolver returns the encoded result of the DNS query to host A1:</t>
            <sourcecode>B6 has address:  10.128.48.62</sourcecode>
          </li>
          <li><t>Host A1 sends a packet out to B6</t>
            <t>Host A1 places its own address as source and the address of host B6 returned by the
              local resolver as destination.
            </t>
            <sourcecode>packet out: | 172.17.1.75 | 10.128.48.62 | payload |</sourcecode>
          </li>
          <li><t>Packet arrives at gateway GWA</t>
            <sourcecode>packet in:  | 172.17.1.75 | 10.128.48.62 | payload |</sourcecode>
            <t>The gateway notices that it does not have mapping for the source address, so it
              creates one on the fly:
            </t>
            <sourcecode>map: 172.17.1.75 = 2001:db8::9 + 1579</sourcecode>
            <t>It replaces source address with the just created corresponding IPREF address. It
              replaces encoded destination address with the original IPREF address returned by
              the DNS query. It also repackages IPv4 packet into IPv6 since the Internet is IPv6.
            </t>
            <sourcecode>packet out: | 2001:db8::9 + 1579 | 2001:db8::8 + 2466 | payload |</sourcecode>
          </li>
          <li><t>Packet arrives at gateway GWB</t>
            <sourcecode>packet in:  | 2001:db8::9 + 1579 | 2001:db8::8 + 2466 | payload |</sourcecode>
            <t>The gateway notices that it does not have encoding for the source IPREF address,
              so it creates one on the fly:
            </t>
            <sourcecode>map: 2001:db8::9 + 1579 = fdee:eeee::5951</sourcecode>
            <t>It replaces source IPREF address with the just created local encoded address. It
              replaces destination IPREF address with the local address of host B6.
            </t>
            <sourcecode>packet out: | fdee:eeee::5951 | 2001:db8:b::28 | payload |</sourcecode>
          </li>
          <li><t>Packet arrives at host B6</t>
            <sourcecode>packet in:  | fdee:eeee::5951 | 2001:db8:b::28 | payload |</sourcecode>
            <t>Host B6 recognizes destination address as its own and consumes the packet. OS passes
              the packet to an application implied by layer 4.
            </t>
          </li>
          <li><t>Host B6 sends a reply back to A1</t>
            <t>Host B6 gets a reply payload from the application, swaps source and destination
              addresses, and sends the packet back to A1.
            </t>
            <sourcecode>packet out: | 2001:db8:b::28 | fdee:eeee::5951 | payload |</sourcecode>
          </li>
          <li><t>Packet arrives at gateway GWB</t>
            <sourcecode>packet in:  | 2001:db8:b::28 | fdee:eeee::5951 | payload |</sourcecode>
            <t>The gateway replaces local source address with corresponding IPREF address previously
              allocated and advertised in DNS. It replaces destination local encoded address with
              the corresponding IPREF address from mapping created earlier.
            </t>
            <sourcecode>packet out: | 2001:db8::8 + 2466 | 2001:db8::9 + 1579 | payload |</sourcecode>
          </li>
          <li><t>Packet arrives at gateway GWA</t>
            <sourcecode>packet in:  | 2001:db8::8 + 2466 | 2001:db8::9 + 1579 | payload |</sourcecode>
            <t>The gateway replaces source IPREF address with the corresponding local encoded
              address from mapping created earlier. It replaces destination IPREF address with
              the local address of host A1. It also realizes that the local network is IPv4, so
              it repackages the packet into IPv4.
            </t>
            <sourcecode>packet out: | 10.128.48.62 | 172.17.1.75 | payload |</sourcecode>
          </li>
          <li><t>Packet arrives at host A1</t>
            <sourcecode>packet in:  | 10.128.48.62 | 172.17.1.75 | payload |</sourcecode>
            <t>Host A1 recognizes destination address as its own and consumes the packet. OS passes
              the packet to the application that sent the original packet.
            </t>
          </li>
        </ol>
        <t>At this point any missing mappings have been allocated. Subsequent packet exchange
          continues without additional allocations.
        </t>

      </section>  <!-- ^^Traversing Address Spaces in Detail^^ -->

      <section><name>Embedding References in IP Packets</name>

        <t>References are network layer entities and the most natural place for embedding them
          would be a network layer headers, such as IPv4 options or IPv6 extension headers.
        </t>
        <t>Unfortunately, many Internet Service Providers drop options and extension headers for
           various reasons. Even if they don't, routers tend to put them on a slow processing
           path resulting in poor performance. For that reason, the most reliable way to embed
           references is to place them in the payload. One common technique to accomplish this is
           tunneling where references could be placed in the payload of the packet being tunneled.
        </t>

        <section><name>IPv4 Option</name>
          <t>With IPv4, references may be embedded in an IPv4 header option <xref target="RFC791"/>.
             It would be a new option type. It would contain an octet with option type and option
             number, an octet with length, and two octets reserved for possible future use while
             padding to four octet boundary. The source and destination references would then follow.
          </t>
          <t>A new option number would be registered with IANA. Until then, experimental option, 30,
             could be used. A separate document should describe it in detail.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section><name>IPv6 Extension Header</name>
          <t>With IPv6, references may be embedded in an IPv6 extension header <xref target="RFC8200"/>.
             It would be a new header type. It would contain an octet with next header type value,
             an octet with length, and two octets reserved for possible future use. This would be
             followed by four octets of padding to 8 octet boundary. Padding octets would not be
             intended for any future use. The source and destination references would then follow.
          </t>
          <t>A new protocol type would be registered with IANA. Until then, experimental protocol,
             254, could be used. A separate document should describe it in detail.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section><name>UDP Tunnel</name>
          <t>Placing references in a UDP tunnel works for both IPv4 and IPv6. In both cases, the
             references are embedded in the form of respective options or extension headers. In
             addition, a tunnel encapsulation record is added. The order of items is as follows:
          </t>
          <ul spacing="compact" empty="true">
            <li>UDP header</li>
            <li>Tunnel encapsulation record</li>
            <li>IPREF option</li>
            <li>Packet payload</li>
          </ul>
          <t>The encapsulation record would consist of four octets. First octet would contain the
             value of TTL copied from the original IP header. The second octet would contain protocol
             number copied from the original IPv4 header or next header value form an IPv6 extension
             header. The third octet would report number of hops detected for incoming packets. The
             fourth octet would be reserved for possible future use while padding to 4 octet boundary.
             The IPREF option would follow in the format matching respective IP protocol, IPv4 or IPv6.
          </t>
          <t>The tunnel would operate at port 1045. This value would be registered with IANA. A
             separate document should describe the tunnel in detail.
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>  <!-- ^^Embedding References^^ -->

      <section><name>Name Resolution Support</name>

        <t>IPREF gateways provide mapping support for name resolution services such as DNS. When
          resolving queries on behalf of local hosts, all returned IPREF addresses must be mapped
          to native addresses of the local network protocol. These are the addresses on the
          <em>encoding</em> network. How is this accomplished may be viewed as a matter of local
          implementation but there may be a need to settle on a standard way of communicating
          with the IPREF gateways to allow compatibility with different resolvers. In that case,
          a separate document should describe such mechanism.
        </t>

      </section>  <!-- ^^ Name Resolution Support ^^ -->

    </section>  <!-- ^^ IPREF Overview ^^ -->

    <section><name>DNS with IPREF</name>

      <t>Similarly to standard IP, IPREF can operate with or without DNS. IPREF addresses may be
        entered and distributed manually. For example, an /etc/hosts file could be used for the
        purpose. Such use makes sense in certain cases. Especially on private networks, the
        practice of using literal addresses is common even if local DNS names are allocated to
        hosts.
      </t>

      <figure anchor="dns-with-ipref"><name>DNS with IPREF</name>
        <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
             Network A    â”‚
                                â•”â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•—
 â”Œâ”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”                 â”‚     â•‘ publc â•‘
 â”‚ host â”‚.75â”ƒ      â”Œâ”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â•¢  DNS  â•‘    A3  AA  2001:db8::9 + 1733
 â”‚  A1  â”œâ”€â”€â”€â”¨  â”â”â”â”â”·â”â”â”â”“  â”‚     â•‘ servr â•‘          â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â–¶
 â””â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”˜   â”ƒ  â”ƒ IPREF â”ƒ:9      â•šâ•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•
            â” â”€â”€â”¨ g-way â” â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€  
 â”Œâ”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”   â”ƒ  â”ƒ  GWA  â”ƒ  
 â”‚ host â”œâ”€â”€â”€â”¨  â”—â”â”â”â”¯â”â”â”â”›  â”‚    Internet
 â”‚  A3  â”‚   â”ƒ      â”‚                                     â•”â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•—
 â””â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”˜          â”‚      â”‚                              â•‘ other â•‘
                   â”‚                                     â•‘ â•”â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•—
     â–²         â•”â•â•â•â•§â•â•â•â•—  â”‚                              â•‘ â•‘ other â•‘
     â”‚         â•‘ local â•‘         â—€â•¶â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€â”€               â•šâ•â•‘ â•”â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•—
     â•°â”€â”€â”€â”€     â•‘  DNS  â•‘     B6  AA  2001:db8::8 + 2466    â•‘ â•‘ other â•‘
               â•‘ rslvr â•‘                                   â•šâ•â•‘  DNS  â•‘
               â•šâ•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•  â”‚                                  â•‘ servr â•‘
                                                             â•šâ•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>IPREF can also take full advantage of DNS <xref target="RFC1035"/>.  IPREF addresses are
        publishable. When resolving names that render IPREF addresses, local resolvers must obtain
        translation into <em>encoded</em> addresses for standard hosts on local networks. Mapping
        to <em>encoded</em> addresses is typically made by IPREF gateways and presented back to
        resolvers which pass them to the querying hosts. In addition, IPREF gateways must be aware
        of all local hosts whose IPREF addresses are published through DNS. This is illustrated
        in <xref target="dns-with-ipref"/>.
      </t>
      <t>Local hosts A1 and A3 resolve DNS names via local resolvers. The resolvers query DNS
        servers on their behalf. Queries may return native IPv4 or IPv6 addresses, or they may
        return IPREF addresses. If the native addresses match local network protocol, the
        resolvers simply return them unchanged, dropping otherwise. In case of IPREF addresses,
        the resolvers obtain a mapping to a native address on an <em>encoded</em> network from
        related IPREF gateways. The gateways may allocate mappings on the fly if missing. The
        resulting <em>encoded</em> IP addresses are then returned to the querying hosts.
      </t>
      <t>If any hosts on local networks advertise services via DNS using IPREF addresses, the
        related IPREF gateways must be made aware of it. The gateways must know which hosts have
        been made available externally and what IPREF addresses have been assigned to them. This
        is typically a semi-static configuration which remains stable for long periods of time.
        The gateways may query those DNS servers for information periodically or some other
        mechanism may be employed to convey that information.
      </t>

      <section><name>DNS Records</name>

        <t>IPREF addresses are unlike well known IPv4 addresses or IPv6 addresses. These addresses
          consist of two components which must be considered as a single address entity. It is not
          possibly to separate references from their companion context addresses. For that reason,
          there is a need for a new resource record type. The new record type is tentatively called
          AA. This record type has not been registered yet. Until such time, a TXT record may be
          used instead. The TXT record simply holds a textual representation of an AA record.
        </t>
        <t> Here are some examples of what the records might look like:
        </t>

        <sourcecode type="dns-rr"> <![CDATA[
    Host-B4     AA      198.51.100.22 + 400
    Host-A5     AA      net-A + 500
    Host-A5     AA      2001:db8::abc:11 + 700
    Host-A5     TXT     "AA net-A + 500"
        ]]> </sourcecode>

        <t>The IP portion may be provided numerically or as a domain name. The format for the reference
          would allow unsigned decimal integers as well as unsigned hex integers. Other formats may be
          defined as well.
        </t>
        <t>The definition of the new resource record, its use, notation, and registration with IANA should
          be described in a separate document.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section><name>Local Network Resolver</name>
        <t>Local network resolver must provide capability to replace IPREF addresses with IP
          addresses from <em>encoded</em> network in consultation with IPREF mappers. It's not
          clear if the details may be left to implementations or whether some sort of an
          exchange protocol should be defined. If so, a separate document would describe it.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section><name>DNS Agent</name>
        <t>A DNS Agent is a component of IPREF mappers that detects if any local hosts are
          advertised as reachable via IPREF addresses. There is a number of existing mechanisms
          to accomplish this. There is probably no need to define another one.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>  <!-- ^^ DNS with IPREF ^^ -->

    <section><name>Using IPREF for Transitioning to IPv6</name>

    <t>Transitioning to IPv6 with IPREF offers significant benefits to both the transitioning
      organizations as well as to the Internet providers, carriers, and operators.
    </t>

      <ol>
        <li><t>Starting point</t>
          <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
             Network A    â”‚    Internet    â”‚    Network B

             â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“    â”‚      IPv6      â”‚    â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“
             â”« IPREF â”£                          â”« IPREF â”£
   IPv4      â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ    â”‚      IPv4      â”‚    â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ      IPv4
  â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•—  â”«  GWA  â”£  â•”â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•—  â”«  GWB  â”£  â•”â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•
          â•‘  â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›  â•‘ â”‚                â”‚ â•‘  â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›  â•‘
          â•šâ•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•                    â•šâ•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•
                          â”‚                â”‚
          ]]></artwork>
          <t>IPREF gateways are installed but not used. All connectivity is pure IPv4.
          </t>
        </li>

        <li><t>Switching traffic to IPREF</t>
          <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
             Network A    â”‚    Internet    â”‚    Network B

   IPv6      â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“    â”‚      IPv6      â”‚    â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“
  â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œâ”« IPREF â”£                          â”« IPREF â”£
   IPv4      â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ    â”‚      IPv4      â”‚    â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ      IPv4
  â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”«  GWA  â”£â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”«  GWB  â”£â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•
             â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›    â”‚                â”‚    â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›
 
                          â”‚                â”‚
          ]]></artwork>
          <t>IPREF gateways are configured. References are assigned. Traffic goes through the
            gateways. All services subject to transition are now accessed via IPREF. Some local
            IPv6 subnets may be setup but they're not used yet.
          </t>
          <t>Transition process at local networks is decoupled from any transition effort taking
            place at peer networks. It is also decoupled from the type of Internet connection.
            Traffic between gateways remains over IPv4 Internet until both ends connect to IPv6
            Internet. This does not affect transitioning of internal networks to IPv6.
          </t>
        </li>

        <li><t>Connecting to IPv6 Internet</t>
          <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
             Network A    â”‚    Internet    â”‚    Network B

   IPv6      â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“    â”‚      IPv6      â”‚    â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“
  â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”« IPREF â”£â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ                   â”« IPREF â”£
   IPv4      â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ    â”‚      IPv4      â”‚    â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ      IPv4
  â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”«  GWA  â”£â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”«  GWB  â”£â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•
             â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›    â”‚                â”‚    â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›

                          â”‚                â”‚
          ]]></artwork>
          <t>Each side connects to IPv6 Internet at their own pace. Local IPv6 subnets may start
            to appear. These are pure IPv6 subnets, no dual stacks. Connectivity between internal
            IPv4/IPv6 subnets is provided by the same IPREF gateway.
          </t>
        </li>

        <li><t>Switching gateway traffic to IPv6</t>
           <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
             Network A    â”‚    Internet    â”‚    Network B

   IPv6      â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“    â”‚      IPv6      â”‚    â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“      IPv6
  â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”« IPREF â”£â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”« IPREF â”£â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ
   IPv4      â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ    â”‚      IPv4      â”‚    â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ      IPv4
  â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”«  GWA  â”£â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â”«  GWB  â”£â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•
             â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›    â”‚                â”‚    â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›

                          â”‚                â”‚
          ]]></artwork>
          <t>After both ends connect to IPv6 Internet, IPREF gateways may switch to passing
            traffic to the IPv6 Internet. Transition process at local networks is not affected
            by this change.
          </t>
        </li>

        <li><t>Dropping IPv4 Internet</t>
            <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
             Network A    â”‚    Internet    â”‚    Network B

   IPv6      â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“    â”‚      IPv6      â”‚    â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“      IPv6
  â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”« IPREF â”£â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”« IPREF â”£â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ â•Œ
   IPv4      â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ    â”‚                â”‚    â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ      IPv4
  â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”«  GWA  â”£                          â”«  GWB  â”£â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•
             â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›    â”‚                â”‚    â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›

                          â”‚                â”‚
          ]]></artwork>
          <t>IPv4 Internet may now be dropped. It takes place early in the process. From the
            Internet's point of view, transition to IPv6 has completed. The Internet does not
            have to wait until every local networks transitions to IPv6. As sites keep dropping
            their IPv4 Internet connections, the entire IPv4 Internet may be taken down well
            before every network out there in the world completes its transition. This is
            possible thanks to decoupling transitioning of local networks from transitioning
            of the Internet itself.
          </t>
          <t>From local networks point of view, the disappearance of IPv4 Internet is invisible.
            It does not affect local transitioning process.
          </t>
        </li>

        <li><t>Switching to IPv6 independently</t>
             <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
             Network A    â”‚    Internet    â”‚    Network B

   IPv6      â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“    â”‚      IPv6      â”‚    â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“      IPv6
  â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”« IPREF â”£â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”« IPREF â”£â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•
   IPv4      â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ    â”‚                â”‚    â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ
  â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”«  GWA  â”£                          â”«  GWB  â”£
             â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›    â”‚                â”‚    â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›

                          â”‚                â”‚
          ]]></artwork>
          <t>Each respective local network switches to IPv6 independently and may progress at
            its own pace. It may elect to stay with a mix IPv4/IPv6 for as long as necessary
            or convenient. This does not affect other networks.
          </t>
        </li>

        <li><t>Completing transition</t>
              <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
             Network A    â”‚    Internet    â”‚    Network B

   IPv6      â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“    â”‚      IPv6      â”‚    â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”“      IPv6
  â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”« IPREF â”£â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â”« IPREF â”£â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•â•
             â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ    â”‚                â”‚    â”ƒ g-way â”ƒ
             â”«  GWA  â”£                          â”«  GWB  â”£
             â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›    â”‚                â”‚    â”—â”â”â”â”â”â”â”â”›

                          â”‚                â”‚
          ]]></artwork>
          <t>Transition is completed when each side switches its internal network to IPv6. All
            internal networks are pure IPv6. The Internet is also pure IPv6. IPREF gateways may
            remain in place to allow communication with third party sites that have not
            transitioned.
          </t>
        </li>
      </ol>

    </section>  <!-- ^^ Using IPREF for Transitioning to IPv6 ^^ -->

    <section><name>Related Technologies</name>

      <t>IPREF works well with related technologies. It does not create conflicts and it does
        not attempt to step on their functionality. 
      </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>IPv4 - IPREF does not replace IPv4, it is an optional add-on to enhance IPv4
             capabilities in the area of address rewriting. It relies on IPv4 in all other
             functions of a network protocol.
          </li>
          <li>IPv6 - IPREF does not replace IPv6, it is an optional add-on to enhance IPv6
             capabilities in the area of address rewriting. It relies on IPv6 in all other
             functions of a network protocol.
          </li>
          <li>NAT - IPREF is an address rewriting technology but operates differently than NAT.
            It operates exclusively at the network layer. It does not reach to upper layer
            protocols or lower layer protocols. For example, there is no manipulation of TCP/UDP
            ports. All layer 4 ports are carried transparently as-is. IPREF does not conflict
            with NAT. In a common configuration, a NAT gateway connects to the Internet without
            any changes. IPREF may operate in parallel to NAT on the same gateway, or it may
            operate on another gateway within the local network 'behind NAT'.
          </li>
          <li>VPN - IPREF deals mostly with addressing. It does not perform typical functions of
             a VPN and it does not replace it. It behaves differently. A typical VPN makes hosts
             of a local network appear as if members of some other local network. Hosts subjected
             to a VPN are managed by that other private networks. This involves a substantial level
             of trust between the two private networks. IPREF does not do any of that. Hosts
             reachable through IPREF are firmly in their respective private networks and remain
             managed by their respective administrators. There may be cases where IPREF may be
             deemed sufficient for a particular purpose but in general IPREF is not a substitute
             for a VPN. IPREF does not conflict with VPNs. A VPN might use IPREF to establish
             a VPN connection.
          </li>
          <li>Firewall - IPREF is not a firewall. While allocation or lack of allocation of
            references has the effect of blocking or allowing access, blocking policy is best
            vested with firewalls. IPREF mappers deal with address rewriting, they are not packet
            filters. There is no conflict between firewalls and IPREF. Firewalls might benefit
            from IPREF specific management features to simplify management and configuration.
          </li>
        </ul>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA">
    <!-- All drafts are required to have an IANA considerations section. See RFC 8126 for a guide.-->
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This memo includes no requests to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security">
      <!-- All drafts are required to have a security considerations section. See RFC 3552 for a guide. -->
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document should not affect the security of the Internet. Documents describing particular
        pieces of IPREF might. Proper security consideration statements would be included in those
        documents.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- NOTE: The Acknowledgements and Contributors sections are at the end of this template -->
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>

        <reference anchor="RFC791" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc791">
        <!-- Manually added reference -->
          <front>
            <title>Internet Protocol</title>
            <author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="J. Postel">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="1981" month="September"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>Internet Protocol Specification
              </t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="791"/>
        </reference>


        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8200.xml"/>
        <!-- The recommended and simplest way to include a well known reference -->

      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119">
        <!-- Manually added reference -->
          <front>
            <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
            <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="1997" month="March"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification. These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents. This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.
              </t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2119"/>
        </reference>

      </references>
    </references>

 </back>
</rfc>
<!-- vim: tabstop=2 softtabstop=2 shiftwidth=2 expandtab
->
